<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An exact journal of the siege of Coni in Piemont with an account of the manner of raising it, by Prince Eugene of Savoy this present year 1691 which has so much mortified the French King, and occasioned the imprisonment of the Sieur de Bulonde, humbly presented to his Royal Highness the Duke of Savoy / by Giovanni Renaldo ... ; sent in a manuscript from Turin to a person of quality in London.</title>
            <author>Rinaldo, Giovanni.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1691</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 61 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A70001</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing E3646</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1520</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11640</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13301756</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13301756</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A70001)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 453:32 or 474:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An exact journal of the siege of Coni in Piemont with an account of the manner of raising it, by Prince Eugene of Savoy this present year 1691 which has so much mortified the French King, and occasioned the imprisonment of the Sieur de Bulonde, humbly presented to his Royal Highness the Duke of Savoy / by Giovanni Renaldo ... ; sent in a manuscript from Turin to a person of quality in London.</title>
                  <author>Rinaldo, Giovanni.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 25, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Tho. Basset ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1691.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Eugene, --  of Savoy, Prince of Savoy, 1663-1736.</term>
               <term>Piemonte (Italy) --  History, Military --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Cuneo (Italy) --  Siege, 1691.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Rekeyed and resubmitted</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98932:1"/>
            <p>AN EXACT JOURNAL OF THE SIEGE of CONI IN PIEMONT. With an Account of the manner of raiſing it, by Prince <hi>Eugene</hi> of <hi>Savoy</hi> this preſent year 1691. which has ſo much mortified the <hi>French</hi> King, and occaſioned the Impriſonment of the Sieur <hi>de Bulonde,</hi> humbly preſented to his Royal Highneſs the Duke of <hi>Savoy:</hi> By <hi>Giovanni Renaldo,</hi> Engineer. <hi>Sent in a Manuſcript from</hi> Turin <hi>to a Perſon of Quallity in</hi> London.</p>
            <q>
               <p>The Famous <hi>Branthome</hi> in his Memoirs, and eſpecially in the Life of the Marſhal <hi>de Briſſac, Tome</hi> 11. ſays. <hi>The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhal</hi> de Briſſac, <hi>after having a conſiderable time beſieged</hi> Coni <hi>was at laſt forced to raiſe the Siege. It has been twice beſieged be fore by the</hi> French, <hi>but always unſucceſsfully; inſomuch that after the raiſing of that Siege by the Marſhal</hi> de Briſſac, Coni <hi>was look'd upon in</hi> France <hi>as a place fatal to the</hi> French <hi>Arms,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Branthome dans la vie du Mareſchal de Briſſac, Tome</hi> 11.</bibl> 
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Baſſet,</hi> at the <hi>George</hi> near St. <hi>Dunſtans</hi>-Church in <hi>Fleetſtreet.</hi> 1691.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98932:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98932:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Siege of <hi>Coni,</hi> thô it has not made that noiſe in the World, as a Siege of <hi>Turin</hi> would have made, in caſe the Deſign laid by the <hi>French</hi> cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ningly enough, had taken its effect, yet it is nevertheleſs very remarkable in all its Circumstances. <hi>Catinat</hi> rendred himſelf Master of <hi>Suze, Nice,</hi> and <hi>Ville Franche,</hi> with little or no difficulty, and <hi>Carmagnole</hi> ſurrendred at ſight of the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. The only place left on this ſide of the Capital City was <hi>Coni,</hi> the Conqueſt of which ſeem'd to the <hi>French</hi> to be of an abſolute neceſſity, for beſides that after the taking of it, they might eaſily draw all manner of Proviſions and Ammuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion out of <hi>Nice</hi> and <hi>Ville Franche</hi> for the uſe of their Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and the reſt of the Conquered Places in <hi>Piemont,</hi> and that it ſecured the paſſage of the Troops that towards Winter were to enter into Quarters in the County of <hi>Nice,</hi> to stop the frequent Incurſions of the <hi>Vaudois,</hi> eſpecially of thoſe of the Valley of <hi>Barcelonette,</hi> it would much have hindred the paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage of the <hi>Germans,</hi> that were a coming to the Dukes Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance; for which reaſons <hi>Feuquieres</hi> and <hi>Bulonde</hi> were
<pb facs="tcp:98932:3"/> ſent with a great detachment from the man Army to take the Place (a haughty way of their ſpeaking when they are going to form a Siege.) <hi>Coni</hi> is a Place but of little ſtrength, moſt of the Fortifications were half ruin'd, and it was expected they would ſurrender at the firſt Summons. But it ſeem'd this inconſiderable Place was deſign'd by Providence to ſtop the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Torrent of the <hi>French</hi> Victories, and to give the first, and the most ſenſible Affront to the <hi>French</hi> King's Arms in <hi>Piemont.</hi> Brave <hi>Julien,</hi> a born Subject of his Majeſty, as Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> having thrown himſelf, with his Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tallion of <hi>French</hi> Refugees in the King's Service, into the Place; defended it with ſo much Vigour and Gallantry, that the <hi>French</hi> were forced, to their everlasting ſhame, to raiſe the Slege. It will be no ſmall Pleaſure to thoſe that read this Journal, to obſerve with what Inſolency <hi>Feuquieres</hi> (ſecure of the Conqueſt) behav'd himſelf before the Place; what ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Letters he wrote to the Beſieged; and how on the contrary his Spirits were oppreſs'd, when he was forc'd to march off. As to the Journal it ſelf, it is certainly one of the trueſt and exactest that ever was writ, in conſideration of which, and of the remoteneſs of the Place, the Reader will eaſily pardon that it comes ſomewhat late.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98932:3"/>
            <head>A JOURNAL OF THE SIEGE of CONI IN PIEMONT: TOGETHER With the Raiſing of it; which has ſo much Mortified the <hi>French</hi> King, and occaſion'd the Impriſonment of the Sieur <hi>de Bulonde.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">Sent in a Manuſcript, from <hi>Turin,</hi> to a Perſon of Quality in <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THE <hi>Town</hi> and <hi>Cittadel</hi> of <hi>Niſſe</hi> were no ſooner ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rendred to the <hi>French,</hi> but Count <hi>de Rouere</hi> Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor of the Province of <hi>Saluſses</hi> and <hi>Coni</hi> expected a <hi>Siege</hi> of the latter. The Friendſhip he entertained with Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>de Julien,</hi> a Subject of his Majeſty of <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> being born in the Principality of <hi>Orange,</hi> who commanded at that time in the Valley of <hi>Barcelone,</hi> together with the great eſteem he had for his Perſon, grounded on the great Exploits he has made in that Country, with one ſingle Battalion of the Troops of his Majeſty of <hi>Great-Britain,</hi> and 200
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98932:4"/> Men of the Regiment of the <hi>French Refugees,</hi> were the motives that perſuaded him to communicate his apprehenſion to him; giving him withal to underſtand, that he did not deſpair of main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining himſelf in that place, his R. H. of <hi>Savoy</hi> had truſted him with, in caſe that with the <hi>New Fortifications</hi> he had cauſed to be raiſed there, he ſhould be aſſured of the aſſiſtance of his Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion. Monſieur <hi>de Julien,</hi> who is of a temper not to let ſlip the leaſt occaſion of ſignalizing himſelf, anſwered the <hi>Governor,</hi> that he ſhould be exceedingly glad of being ſerviceable to him in what place ſoever he would be pleaſed to call him.</p>
            <p>This great readineſs of his obliged the <hi>Governor</hi> to ſollicite at his <hi>R. Highnèſs's Court</hi> for the <hi>Lieutenant Colonel's</hi> retreat out of the Valley of <hi>Barcelone,</hi> and orders being ſent accordingly, a great time before the <hi>Action</hi> of <hi>Meironne,</hi> (where he with his ſingle Battalion defeated a Body of between 3 and 4000 of the <hi>French,</hi> killing 4 or 500 of them upon the ſpot,) he marched towards <hi>Coni;</hi> and after he had made, for two or three days time, ſeveral <hi>Marches</hi> and <hi>Counter-marches</hi> round about this place, heat laſt entered into it, under <hi>pretence</hi> of refreſhing him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf and his <hi>Battalion</hi> there, after the great Fatigues they had ſuffered during the Winter; ten days after it the Garriſon marched out of the place, in order to join the <hi>Army,</hi> with the two hundred Men above-mentioned, and the Guard of it was committed to the ſingle <hi>Battalion</hi> of <hi>de Julien.</hi> He had ſcarce been there one Month, but the <hi>Governor</hi> was informed, that a <hi>detachment</hi> of four thouſand Men, Horſe and Foot, were ſent out of Monſieur <hi>Catinat's Army,</hi> under the command of Monſieur <hi>de Feuquieres, Mareſchal de Camp</hi> of the <hi>French</hi> King's Forces, to inveſt <hi>Coni,</hi> and it was believed the <hi>main Army</hi> would follow them on their Heels to form the <hi>Siege</hi> of it; the <hi>French</hi> flatter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing themſelves to have as cheap a Bargain of this place, as they had of that of <hi>Carmagnole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Upon this advice the <hi>Governor</hi> divided the Poſts amongſt his <hi>little Garriſon,</hi> it being compoſed of Monſieur <hi>de Julien's Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion</hi> of 500 Men, of 120 <hi>new raiſed Soldiers,</hi> ſome <hi>Militia</hi> of the Country, and the <hi>Burghers:</hi> He gave orders for the
<pb facs="tcp:98932:4"/> Baking of a great quantity of Bread; and to advance the <hi>Fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations</hi> that were yet unfiniſhed. He formed his <hi>Council of War</hi> of the Counts of <hi>Prouane, Commendant;</hi> and <hi>de Vibau, Vice-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendant;</hi> of Lievtenant-Colonel <hi>de Julien; de Guibert,</hi> firſt <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineer</hi> of <hi>Savoy; Chouet,</hi> Captain in the Regiment of <hi>Savoy,</hi> and <hi>Major</hi> of the place; and the <hi>Engineer Garroue.</hi> In fine, he did all that could be expected from a wiſe and experienced Officer, in order to avoid being either ſurprized or prevented by the Enemy.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 11th. The Sieur <hi>de Feuquieres,</hi> being puſſed up with the Succeſs the Arms of <hi>France</hi> had met with at <hi>Carmagnole,</hi> and flattering himſelf with the ſurrender of <hi>Coni</hi> without the leaſt reſiſtance, after he had plundered the Church of St. <hi>Renin,</hi> ſent a Letter by a Peaſant of <hi>Villefalet</hi> to the <hi>Syndics</hi> of the Town, who having delivered the latter without opening it, together with the bearer into the <hi>Governor</hi>'s Hands, he ordered the latter to be ſecured, and being retired into a private Room with L. Col. <hi>de Julien, Guibert,</hi> and <hi>Chouet,</hi> he read the Letter which was written in theſe following terms:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>I Am inform'd that you have in your Place a Battalion of <hi>French</hi> Heretiks, and ſome Peaſants in Arms, that have abandon'd their Houſes on purpoſe to follow a Trade that does not become them. The quick ſurrender of <hi>Carmagnole</hi> gives you no reaſon to hope for better Terms; and I have ſent you this Letter to let you know that the King's Army draws near to your Place, and that in caſe you do not ſpeedily ſend to me your Deputies, in order to obtain a good Capitulation, I am reſolved, as many Hours there ſhall paſs before their arrival, to burn as many Villages within ten Leagues round your Place. I take no notice at all of the <hi>French</hi> Hereticks, I am glad to ſee them ſhut up in a Dungeon, and Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>de Julien</hi> ſhall not be able to prevent your Submiſſion. I am, Gentlemen,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours Feuquieres</signed>
                     <dateline>From the Camp of <hi>Taranteſque, </hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>June</hi> the 11th. 1691.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:98932:5"/>
            <p>After the reading of this Letter, the three Officers that were then with the <hi>Governor</hi> did agree with him, that before they ſhew'd it to the Counſel of the Town, it would be neceſſary to ſound their Inclinations, and the Governor having at the ſame time told L. Col. <hi>de Julien,</hi> that he ſhould be very glad to know the diſpoſition of the Officers of his Battalion, he did aſſure him that it was ſuch as ought to be expected from Men of Honour; and having ſent for them in the great Court of the Palace, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted them with the Threatnings the Sieur <hi>de Feuquieres</hi> had made them, he told them, <hi>That he was reſolved to give them a good Example by his Behaviour as he had done formerly, and that he himſelf had ſeen the Succours depart from his Royal Highneſs's Army, on a Journey he had made thither in 36 Hours;</hi> in a word, he knew ſo well how to perſwade them, that all his Captains (moſt of which were much diſpleaſed for not having paid them their Arrears) forgot their diſpleaſure anſwering their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander, <hi>That they would follow him where-ever he ſhould lead them, according to their former behaviour, that they were una<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimouſly reſolved rather to die upon the ſpot, than to betray their Truſt, or to fail in their Duty.</hi> The L. Colonel being raviſh'd to find them in ſo reſolute a diſpoſition, conducted them into the Governor's Chamber; telling him, that his whole Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talion was, as well as himſelf, reſolved to do their Duty, and that every one of them was full of Zeal for His Royal Highneſs's Service; he added, that the <hi>Councel of the Town,</hi> who in ſeveral Sieges had convinced their Sovereign of their Faithfulneſs and Loyalty, would undoubtedly give yet greater proofs of it on this occaſion, ſeeing themſelves encouraged by the <hi>French Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugees,</hi> who though they were altogether <hi>Strangers,</hi> were ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſs willing to Sacrifice themſelves out of love to them, The <hi>Governor</hi> anſwered, that he was perſwaded of the Courage and Zeal of the <hi>French Proteſtants;</hi> and having ſent for the whole Body of the <hi>Councel of the Town,</hi> acquainted them with his and the <hi>Garriſons</hi> reſolution, and he heard with joy that their incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nations were accordingly: Whereupon he delivered to them the Sieur <hi>de Feuquieres</hi>'s Letter; which by his conſent they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered in this following manner:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98932:5"/>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>WE <hi>have received the Letter which your Excellency has done us the Honour to write to us. The Zeal and Eager<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, which on all occaſions you ſhow for the ſervice of his Most Chriſtian Majesty, ſets us ſo Noble a Pattern, that we cannot chuſe but imitate it in this point. Therefore we hope you will not take it ill, that we are reſolved to do our Duty, and to be Faithful to our Sovereign. As for the Misfortune we are threatned with, we hope your Excellency's Generoſity will divert it from us. We are with reſpect,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>SIR,</salute>
                     <signed>Your Excellency's moſt Humble and moſt Obedient Servants.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This Anſwer was ſent to the Sieur <hi>de Feuquieres</hi> by the ſame Peaſant that was the Bearer of his Letter, who was glad of having eſcaped the Rope, which according to his demerits he had been threatned with.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 12th. between 14 and 15 a Clock of <hi>Italy,</hi> or between 10 and 11 in the Morning, the Enemy <hi>inveſted</hi> the Town. As ſoon as their Troops drew near, the <hi>Governor</hi> gave orders to <hi>diſcharge</hi> the Cannons; the firſt Bullet carried away a <hi>whole rank</hi> of four Dragoons, according to our own ſight, and their own relation afterwards, which obliged them to a little <hi>retreat.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Towards Night another Letter was ſent by the Sieur <hi>de Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieres,</hi> in theſe following terms:</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I</hi> Did not think fit to Anſwer your Letter, before I had taken a full view of your Place. It is indeed in too bad a condition to think on defending it. Do not expect an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Capitulation, if you put us to the troubles of diſcharg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our Cannons, and make a ſerious reflexion, I beſeech you, of what I tell you. Monſieur <hi>de Julien's</hi> Battalion, if it was much ſtronger than it is, will not prevent what you are to ſuffer, and which you may now avoid. It will hereafter be
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:98932:6"/> too late to think on a Capitulation, which you may now expect.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <hi>I am,</hi>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                     <signed>Yours, Feuquieres.</signed>
                     <dateline>From the Camp before <hi>Coni, </hi> 
                        <date>
                           <hi>June</hi> 12. 1691.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>There was ſent no Anſwer to this ſecond Letter. Every Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy did only think on making a vigorous Defence, and to give the <hi>Enemy</hi> good Impreſſions of the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the <hi>Place,</hi> as well as of the <hi>Bravery</hi> of the <hi>Defendents.</hi> The Body of the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> was very anxious in diſcovering the Sentiments of the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders</hi> and the <hi>Troops;</hi> and ſinding in them nothing but what was recommendable, were delivered from their <hi>panick Fears,</hi> and encouraged to forget nothing that might contribute to the <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Place,</hi> and their <hi>Liberties.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſame day the <hi>Governor</hi> thought fit to <hi>divide the Poſts,</hi> which was done in this manner: To the Count <hi>de Provane Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendant</hi> was committed the Guard of the <hi>Gate of Turin,</hi> of the <hi>Baſtions of Notre Dame,</hi> of the <hi>Lorme de Carait,</hi> with the <hi>Gates of Succours</hi> that are in this Precinct; as alſo of the <hi>demi-Baſtions of l'Orme,</hi> that are on the ſide of the River <hi>de Gez:</hi> The <hi>Vice-Commendant Vibau</hi> was to defend the <hi>Baſtions</hi> of <hi>de l'Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal of St. Francis</hi> and <hi>St. Ann,</hi> with the <hi>Gate of Succours,</hi> and to him was committed the Care of ſending <hi>Ammunition</hi> to the ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral <hi>Magazines:</hi> The <hi>Commander</hi> of the <hi>Batallion</hi> of the <hi>French Refugees</hi> had the Guard of the <hi>Two half Moons;</hi> the Place where the <hi>Cittadel</hi> was formerly, and where at preſent there is only a bad <hi>Glacis,</hi> a <hi>Counterſcarp,</hi> and a <hi>Covert-way,</hi> that goes from the <hi>Gate of Turin</hi> as far as to the <hi>Baſtion of St. James,</hi> towards a dead Angle, which is called <hi>the Cittatelle,</hi> the <hi>Gate of Turin,</hi> the <hi>Baſtion of St. James,</hi> the <hi>Gates of Succours,</hi> the <hi>Rivas</hi> and <hi>la Pierre.</hi> As for the whole <hi>Covert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> it was abandoned for want of Troops to guard it; and it was not ſecured till after the arrival of the <hi>Succours,</hi> after which this Order was changed. The <hi>Engeneer Guibert</hi> had the dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of all the <hi>Works</hi> that were to be made during the <hi>Siege;</hi> and he had under him the <hi>Engeneer Garroue</hi> to aſſiſt him in the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98932:6"/> Execution of his Deſigns: All the <hi>Commanders</hi> were to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form him of what did happen in their Poſts, and to give im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately notice of it to the <hi>Governor,</hi> who charged himſelf with the whole weight of the Affairs in general, retaining near his Perſon the <hi>Major</hi> and the <hi>Adjutants,</hi> in order to carry to every Body his Orders.</p>
            <p>The Troops were ſent each to their Poſts, where they continued always, becauſe there were none to relieve them.</p>
            <p>The Body of the Reſerve in the Place was very inconſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable.</p>
            <p>The Night between the 12th and the 13th was paſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Allarm; but our Muſqueteers ſired continually, to force the Enemy to begin their <hi>Approaches</hi> from afar off.</p>
            <p>The 13th. between 10 and 11 a Clock before Noon, we ſaw the Enemy's <hi>Horſe</hi> March towards us with great haſte, followed by ſome of their <hi>Foot,</hi> which made us believe that our <hi>Succours</hi> was a coming. Our Cannons, that were placed on that ſide playing upon them, made them March yet with greater precipitation, and killed ſome of their Horſe. The <hi>Governor</hi> ſent 200 <hi>Refugees,</hi> commanded by their Lievtenant-Colonel, out of the Place, to favour the entring of our <hi>Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours,</hi> in caſe they were upon their March; but it was ſound a miſtake. A little time after it two Deſerters came over to us, relating that the Sieur <hi>de Feuquieres</hi> had at the moſt but four thouſand Men with him, <hi>viz.</hi> three Regiments of <hi>Foot,</hi> and the reſt of <hi>Horſe</hi> and <hi>Dragoons,</hi> three pieces of Cannon, but no Mortar-pieces; but that he expected a conſiderable re-inforcement from <hi>Monſieur Catinat</hi>'s Army, where there were but lately arrived eighteen <hi>Mortar-pieces</hi> and fifty three of Cannon; and that the Army that was coming to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiege us was to conſiſt of between eight and nine thouſand Men.</p>
            <p>The 14th. two hours before Day-break, the Sieur <hi>de Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieres</hi> deſign'd to ſurprize a Poſt of the <hi>Cittadel;</hi> to which purpoſe he commanded thither two Companies of <hi>Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deers,</hi> who having made ſome noiſe in mounting towards
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98932:7"/> an old <hi>Breach,</hi> an <hi>Allarm</hi> was made, and five Soldiers with their Officer fired upon the Enemy, which they endured without ſaying one Word. The <hi>Engineers</hi> and ſome Officers were immediately called: The <hi>Governor</hi> ask'd what they had ſeen? <hi>Guibert</hi> ſaid they had ſeen no Body. The <hi>Governor</hi> anſwered, ſome Body muſt have been there, that it was no <hi>illuſion,</hi> and that he himſelf had heard a noiſe: Whereupon the place was re-inforced, and the Soldiers ordered to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue their firing. In the Morning we diſcovered that the Enemy had endeavoured to make themſelves Maſters of this <hi>Poſt,</hi> but that the great Fire which was made by our Men had put them into a great confuſion, and turn'd ſeveral of them down into the River <hi>Gez;</hi> for we found 12 Muſquets, ſome Hats, a Perriwig, a Sword, and two wounded Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers, who inform'd us of the Enemies, and that forty <hi>Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nadeers</hi> had been made uſeleſs on this occaſion.</p>
            <p>The ſame day <hi>Palliſadoes</hi> were ſet up on that place where the Enemy had mounted, and this was the only <hi>Attack</hi> they made during the Siege towards the <hi>Cittadel;</hi> we pull'd down the Bridge of the <hi>Gate of Turin,</hi> which was no more opened, and we made uſe of the <hi>Gate of Succours</hi> that leads into the <hi>Cittadel;</hi> ſome <hi>new Works</hi> were alſo ordered to be made that Day, and Lievtenant-Colonel <hi>de Julien</hi> poſted a <hi>detachment</hi> of the <hi>Refugees</hi> to cover the <hi>Workmen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Towards Night ſome <hi>Volunteers</hi> diſlodged a Guard of the Enemies Dragoons, that had poſted themſelves near the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver <hi>Gez,</hi> and the Night was paſt without Allarm.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Governor</hi> was informed that <hi>Count de Bernez</hi> that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted our Succours, was departed from <hi>Mondovi,</hi> and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards five a Clock at Night, having received advice that he was near the Place, he ſent out a <hi>detachment</hi> of three hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Men, under the command of <hi>Monſieur de Julien;</hi> and his orders were proclaimed through the whole Town, That all thoſe that were provided with a Horſe ſhould mount on Horſe-back, with their Arms, in order to meet our <hi>Succours;</hi> which was punctually executed. The Commendant <hi>de
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98932:7"/> Prouane</hi> poſted his Men ſo advantageouſiy, that he beat back the Enemy, who preſs'd our Succours with great vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gour. Count <hi>Bernez</hi> did confeſs, that without his Sally, the Enemy would have made a great ſlaughter amongſt his Men; we loſt only 14 of our Men, a Servant, and a Serjeant, and ſeven or eight of them were killed by the <hi>Refugees,</hi> who took them for the Enemy; 'tis true, that the Peaſants of <hi>Mondovi</hi> ſuffered very much, 40 of them being kill'd upon the ſpot, and ſeveral wounded; which was the reaſon that the Sieur <hi>de Feuquieres</hi> bragg'd, that on this occaſion he had kill'd 600 Men of our Succours, that the reſt had hidden themſelves in the Wood, and entered during Night into the City, which is ſo far from Truth, that between ſix and ſeven a Clock at Night their Horſe were charged by our <hi>detachment,</hi> that forced them to repaſs the River <hi>Gez</hi> with great precipitation and diſorder; and afterwards the Engineer <hi>Guibert</hi> having given notice to the <hi>Commendant,</hi> that there was ſtill ſome Ammunition left upon the Bridge <hi>de Sture,</hi> he made half a Tour to the Right with his Troop, who took it and carried it into the Place before Night. And in this manner the <hi>Count de Bernez</hi> entered into <hi>Coni</hi> with the <hi>Succours.</hi> It was indeed one of the boldeſt and happieſt Actions we have heard of theſe many years; and it cannot be denied, but that the <hi>Sieur de Feuquieres</hi> had mightily forgot himſelf on this occaſion, ſince there was nothing eaſier than to deſtroy this <hi>Succour,</hi> it being only compoſed of 280 of the Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Saxe-Coburg, (The Emperors Troops;)</hi> 130 Soldiers of the Regiment of <hi>Wirtemberg, (The King of Spain's Troops;) 120 Italians of the ſame Troops;</hi> and the Regiment of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſſes,</hi> conſiſting of 450 Soldiers, commanded by the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs <hi>de Vauqueres,</hi> Son to the Prince <hi>de la Ciſterne;</hi> there were beſides 50 <hi>Dragoons</hi> that were not deſigned for the Place, but only to Convoy the Count <hi>de Bernez,</hi> he having order to retreat after he had thrown the Succours into the Place; but beſides the difficulty of his retreat this <hi>Mareſchal de Camp</hi> did not think fit to leave a Place that was inveſted and going to be beſieged.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:98932:8"/>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 16th. The <hi>Garriſon</hi> not being paid, the <hi>Governor,</hi> who has behaved himſelf very prudently during the Siege, and who has always done more than he promiſed, found ſome means to pay them; and having afterward taken a full <hi>review</hi> of all the <hi>Garriſon,</hi> it was found that we had only loſt fourteen Soldiers, one Serjeant, and a <hi>Valet-de-Chambre</hi> to the Lievtenant-Colonel of the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Governor</hi> ſent a <hi>Tambour</hi> into the Enemies Camp to challenge the two laſt; but he was anſwered that they had not heard of them.</p>
            <p>The ſame day the Guards of the Poſts were changed. The <hi>Refugees</hi> remain'd upon the Poſt of the <hi>Cittadel,</hi> the <hi>Bastions of St. Anne, St. James,</hi> at the <hi>Gate of the Succours,</hi> and of <hi>Niſſe,</hi> at the <hi>dead Angle,</hi> and at the <hi>Rivas,</hi> and poſſeſs'd themſelves beſides of the <hi>Baſtion de Carail;</hi> the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes</hi> poſſeſs'd themſelves of the <hi>Half Moon of Rouere,</hi> that was in very good order and lined with Stone, they had alſo the Guard of the <hi>Gate of Niſſe,</hi> till to <hi>the Bastion of L'orme; Saxe-Coburg</hi> was poſted in the <hi>Covert-way</hi> from the <hi>Place of Arms</hi> to the <hi>Counterguard</hi> of the <hi>Half-Moon Balbiane,</hi> that is only made of Earth and in a bad condition, they had alſo one part of the Guard of the <hi>Bastion de Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rail</hi> and <hi>Notre-Dame;</hi> the <hi>Italians</hi> were partly put upon the <hi>Baſtion de l'Hoſpital</hi> and <hi>St. Francois,</hi> and partly upon the <hi>Counterſcarp</hi> that regards the River <hi>Sture;</hi> the new-raiſed Companies guarded <hi>la Pierre</hi> and the <hi>Environs;</hi> the <hi>Half-Bastion de L'orme</hi> was guarded by the <hi>Burghers;</hi> and the Surplus with the <hi>Militia</hi> were poſted in the Main Place, in caſe of an Allarm or Attack: The <hi>Governor</hi> remained upon the <hi>Place of Arms,</hi> with the <hi>Body of Reſerve,</hi> in order to ſend ſome Succours to the Attacked Poſts; the <hi>Counts de Prouane</hi> and <hi>Vibau</hi> had alſo their Poſts aſſign'd them; the <hi>Count de Bernez</hi> and the <hi>Marqueſs de Vauqueres</hi> were near the <hi>Half-Moon Rouere;</hi> and the Lievtenant-Colonel <hi>de Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lien</hi> was with his Battalion. Theſe <hi>Commanders</hi> viſited the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98932:8"/> Poſts from time to time, and the <hi>Governor</hi> made exactly his <hi>round</hi> to make every Body mindful of his Duty.</p>
            <p>The 17th. we were inform'd that <hi>Monſieur de Bulonde</hi> came to join the <hi>Sieur de Feuquieres</hi> with a conſiderable <hi>re-inforcement;</hi> whereupon the <hi>Governor</hi> call'd a <hi>Counſel of War,</hi> wherein it was concluded, that the <hi>Germans</hi> ſhould be relieved out of the <hi>Out-works,</hi> as not thinking it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venient to expoſe the beſt Troops at the very firſt Attacks; and accordingly they were reliev'd by the <hi>Refugees,</hi> and the <hi>Germans</hi> were poſted in the <hi>Cittadel,</hi> and ſome other places of the City. The <hi>Refugees</hi> being well pleaſed with their new Poſt, remained there during the whole <hi>Siege.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At Night we were always upon our Guards expecting the Enemy would open their <hi>Trenches.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 18th. The <hi>Enemy</hi> receiv'd another <hi>re-inforce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> and about 2 a Clock the next Morning they <hi>opened the Trenches,</hi> near an <hi>antient Wall</hi> that runs along a <hi>Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tin,</hi> oppoſite to the <hi>Baſtions of Notre-Dame and Carail,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 300 Foot from the <hi>Palliſadoes,</hi> and the <hi>Half-Moon Balbiane,</hi> which they advanced ſtrait to the <hi>Gallows,</hi> about 350 Foot in length, they met in one place with ſo hard a ground, that we heard it was like to have made them mad: So ſoon as we perceiv'd it, our Men fired furiouſly upon them from the Out-works, during the remainder of the Night. Our <hi>Gunners</hi> diſcharged unadvertently a Cannon from the <hi>Bastion de Carail</hi> that kill'd four of the Refugees and two of their Officers that were poſted at the <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard,</hi> guarded by their Company of <hi>Granadeers,</hi> with 60 other Soldiers.</p>
            <p>The ſame Night twenty Men made a <hi>Sally</hi> to retard the Works of the Enemy, and they came back with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out loſs, except that of a Serjeant of the <hi>Refugees,</hi> who was kill'd by a Muſquet-ſhot from the <hi>Baſtion of Notre-Dame.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:98932:9"/>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 19th. The <hi>Enemy</hi> advanced their <hi>Trenches,</hi> to which 300 Workmen were employed inſtead of 600 that had been buſie about it during Night.</p>
            <p>At Night they continued their <hi>approaches,</hi> and made a <hi>Battery</hi> of 6 pieces of Canon, and another of four <hi>Mortar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pieces,</hi> with which they play'd upon the <hi>City;</hi> we found that they had thrown 36 Bombs into the Place and the Out-works, whilſt in the mean time they continued their Works under the favour of a <hi>Corn-field</hi> that covered them, and which has ſaved them a great many of their Men during the <hi>Siege.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 20th. By break of Day they play'd continually upon us with ſix pieces of Cannon, and continued to throw their Bombs into the City, during the whole Day; but the little harm they did us gave a freſh courage to the Inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitants. Several of the <hi>French Refugees,</hi> that had never ſeen this ſort of Engines, were preſently uſed to it, and did not mind them at all, althô their Poſts were the moſt viſited by them.</p>
            <p>The Enemy did not at all endeavour to make a breach with his Cannon, of which ſome were 24, others 36 Poun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; but they always ſhot at random, ſometimes toward a Steeple, ſometimes amongſt the Houſes, ſometimes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Baſtion of Carail,</hi> where we annoy'd them very much with two pieces of Cannon, and ſometimes towards the <hi>Baſtion of Notre-Dame,</hi> where we had alſo planted ſome Cannons. Some young Men that found ſome <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets</hi> in the Ditches and the Streets carried them to the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor,</hi> who at firſt gave them a French Livre, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards fifteen pence a piece; but the number of them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing very much, he gave them at laſt but five pence a piece.</p>
            <p>This day was ſpent in working on both ſides. The Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my took Poſt at a <hi>Silk-Mill,</hi> ſituated upon the River <hi>Sture,</hi> from whence they fired furiouſly upon thoſe that guarded the <hi>Countuergard de Carail.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98932:9"/>
            <p>During Night two Houſes were burn'd, either by the neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligency of ſome particular Perſons, or the Bombs of the Enemy. This Fire Allarm'd ſomewhat the Inhabitants; but they were appeaſed by the <hi>Governors</hi> order to remove all Wood, and other combuſtible things from the top of the Houſes.</p>
            <p>A little <hi>Sally</hi> was made, but without any effect. Our Muſqueteers in the Out-works continued their Firing, as uſually, to hinder the approaches of the Enemy, who ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded the whole <hi>Front</hi> from the <hi>Counterguard de Carail</hi> till to the point of the <hi>Baſtion of Notre-Dame,</hi> which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended exactly the Poſts that were guarded by the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugees.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 21ſt. The whole day was ſpent in Firing on both ſides, but the Enemy had the advantage of the Bombs.</p>
            <p>At night the <hi>Counſel of War</hi> did aſſemble, where all the Officers that were deſign'd to be there were preſent, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept <hi>Monſieur de Julien.</hi> It was there repreſented by the <hi>Engineer Guibert, That beſides that our Troops were extreme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly harras'd, it was impoſſible to maintain the Covert way with ſo few Forces, it being in a bad poſture, and every where ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rounded by the Enemies Works. That by endeavouring to maintain it, we would run the hazard to loſe all the Men that guarded it; eſpecially the French Refugees, who had behav'd themſelves ſo courageouſly, and who were exactly poſted to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Attack and the Approaches of the Enemy, who un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubtedly would in great numbers fall upon them, in order to poſſeſs themſelves of the Covert-way and the Half-Moon, which they knew to be almoſt in no poſture of defence. That therefore it would be more prudent to keep only the Sallying places of Arms, and to abandon all the reſt; eſpecially, when according to the Project that was made, a good Body of Men ſhould be put into the Half-moons and the Counterguard of Carail.</hi> This advice ſeem'd to be very rational, and the <hi>Counſel</hi> having reſolv'd upon't accordingly, the <hi>Engineer</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98932:10"/> went towards Night into the <hi>Covert-way,</hi> to inform the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mander</hi> of the <hi>Refugees</hi> of it, (who did not ſtir from that place night and day;) he acquainted him with what he had propoſed to the Counſel, and that they all had given him their conſent, to which <hi>Monſieur de Julien</hi> anſwered, <hi>That it was a very wiſe and recommendable reſolution, but ſince it only aim'd at the preſervation of our Men, if they would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him, he did not think fit to abandon a place without blows, which he had guarded with ſo much care from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Siege; and ſince we were in expectation the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my would poſſeſs themſelves of it with their Swords in their Hands, he would maintain it as long as it was poſſible with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expoſing his Men to be cut in pieces: That he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trive the matter in ſuch a manner, that advice ſhould be given him in what condition each of his Poſts were during the Attack, and that as ſoon he would find one in a condition to be forced, he would ſave the reſt of the Men in the beſt manner he ſhould be capable of.</hi> To which the <hi>Engineer</hi> replyed: <hi>Sir, you have reaſon not to be willing to abandon a part of your Poſts which your Men have guarded till now; but you will certainly be forced to t: Nevertheleſs, I am going to inform the Regiment of</hi> Saluſſes <hi>of your deſign, and that conſequently they are to guard their Out-works as well as you do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>At night the <hi>Muſqueteers</hi> continued their Firing, and an hour before day-break a <hi>detachment</hi> of <hi>Dragoons</hi> made a <hi>falſe Attack</hi> at the <hi>Counterguard de Carail;</hi> whereupon a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachment was ſent thither by the <hi>Commendant, de Prouane</hi> but afterwards he found it to be only a falſe Attack.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 22d. By break of day the <hi>Enemy</hi> made the <hi>true Attack,</hi> after a <hi>Signal</hi> given by eight Bombs and three Cannons: They attack'd one of the moſt advanced places guarded by the Refugees, who behaved themſelves with ſo much bravery, and made ſo vigorous an oppoſition, as could hardly be expected from ſuch a handful of Men, againſt 500 <hi>Granadeers, 500 Fuſileers,</hi> and 200 <hi>Dragoons,</hi> ſeconded by two Regiments of Foot; but whereas they were a little too
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98932:10"/> eager in ſome places, we had great paines to ſave thoſe that were not killed in the Attack.</p>
            <p>We ought here to render Juſtice to our <hi>Enemy,</hi> and confeſs that they behaved themſelves very well, ſince they made themſelves Maſters of our Outworks with their Swords in their Hands, forced a way to the <hi>Half-moon</hi> in three places, and mingled themſelves amongſt our Men into the <hi>Ditch</hi> of the place, with an extraordinary Courage and Boldneſs. One of their <hi>Colonels</hi> was killed near the <hi>Gate of the Succours;</hi> and indeed he was not the only Man of their Officers that were left behind in the Ditch. The <hi>Refugees</hi> having put ſome of their Men into the <hi>Courtine</hi> of the <hi>Baſtion de Carail</hi> and <hi>Notre-Dame,</hi> fired ſo furiouſly upon the <hi>Enemy,</hi> who was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready much weakned, that it was impoſſible for them to maintain themſelves in the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> nay to lodge them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the <hi>Counterſcarp;</hi> and they confeſſed themſelves that it had been too hot to remain there. Their <hi>Dragoons,</hi> who had loſt their Officers, were the firſt that run away; and we ought not to be ſurpriz'd, that all the reſt followed them in great diſorder; ſince we continued to Fire upon them from the <hi>Counterguard of the Baſtions de Carail</hi> and <hi>Notre-Dame,</hi> and being aſſiſted by thoſe of the <hi>Courtine,</hi> left the <hi>Enemy</hi> no time to <hi>lodge</hi> themſelves, except they had been willing to loſe their whole Army, which at that time con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſted of twelve Regiments of Foot, two of Horſe, and two of Dragoons.</p>
            <p>The Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes</hi> annoy'd the Enemy very much with the Cannon from their Poſts, that were not attacked by the Enemy, the Cannon of the <hi>Baſtion of Notre-Dame</hi> broke twice their Squadron of Horſe, and this attack laſted an hour and a half. Our loſs conſiſted for the greateſt part of <hi>French Refugees,</hi> and of 7 or 8 <hi>Germans;</hi> three Captains were kill'd upon the ſpot, beſides one who dyed afterwards of his wounds, one Enſign, one Sergeant, and 30 Common Soldiers. Of the number of the wounded were the Lieutenant Colonel, who was wounded in his Hand, one Captain, one Enſign,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98932:11"/> two Sergeants, and 55 Soldiers. It would be to no purpoſe to ſay with ſeveral others, that the <hi>Refugees</hi> regain'd the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> with their Swords in their Hands, ſince the <hi>Enemy</hi> will certainly deny it, becauſe they retreated without being pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſued, and were only forced to leave their Poſt, by the great Fire that was made upon them from our <hi>Baſtions.</hi> Lieutenant Colonel <hi>de Julien,</hi> who was the Man in the World that prais'd moſt this bold Action of theirs, anſwered to thoſe that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plemented him for having regained this <hi>Outwork,</hi> and driven the Enemy out of the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> with the Sword in his Hand, and planted the <hi>Standard of England</hi> upon one point of the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> (the latter of which he really did,) <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, If you had ſeen the whole courſe of this Action, you would not trouble me with ſuch complements; for if I have forced the Enemy to abandon all our Outworks, it was by reaſon of the great Fire I ordered to be made by our Men, after which, 'tis true, that I went out and conducted them into Half-moon, but I found no Enemy there, no more than in the Covert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way and upon the Counterguard:</hi> Confirming by this Anſwer of his, that it is very Natural to Men of a Noble and Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Mind, to render Juſtice to all the World, and by no means to accept of praiſes they have not deſerved, neither to hear thoſe but with uneaſineſs which they have bought with the very hazard of their Lives.</p>
            <p>The loſs of the <hi>Enemy</hi> was far more conſiderable than we at firſt imagined, we talk'd then only of 5 or 6 hundred of their Men kill'd, but afterwards we were informed by the <hi>Deſerters,</hi> as well as the <hi>Priſoners of War,</hi> (amongſt which there were ſeveral conſiderable Officers,) that in this Action a thouſand of their Soldiers had been kill'd, the Flower of their Troops, with about ſeventy <hi>Officers</hi> kill'd or wounded, and amongſt them ſeveral that were in great eſteem in their Army, we have ſix of them wounded in our place. The reſt of the day we had no diſturbance at all given us, the Enemy being almoſt affraid to ſhow their Faces; they only plaid with their Cannon, and threw ſome Bombs and Stones into the City.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:98932:11"/>
            <p>We buried our Dead, and thoſe of the <hi>Enemy</hi> that were found in our <hi>Outworks:</hi> Some freſh Men were put into the <hi>Covert-way,</hi> and we contented our ſelves to guard the <hi>Places of Arms,</hi> upon each of which there were poſted ten Soldiers with one Sergeant.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Enemy</hi> did not at all deſire leave to carry away their Dead, nor did they enquire after a <hi>Colonel</hi> of theirs, and ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral other <hi>Officers of Note,</hi> that were left behind upon the place, and indeed we ſaw ſeveral of them that lay upon the <hi>Counterſcarpe</hi> lifting up their Heads, as if they begg'd their Friends aſſiſtance, which yet was not granted them till at Night.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Enemy</hi> had advanced their <hi>Trenches</hi> within 20 or 25 yards of the <hi>Palliſadoes,</hi> and it was from thence they endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, without puſhing more forward, to poſſeſs themſelves of our Outworks.</p>
            <p>At Night they endeavoured to draw near <hi>to the place of Arms,</hi> near the <hi>covered way,</hi> but were hindred by the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual firing of our <hi>Muſqueteers;</hi> the <hi>Enemy</hi> threw ſome <hi>Bombs</hi> and Stones into the place, and the former being all ſpent, they ſent for more from <hi>Carmagnole.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 23d. The <hi>Enemy</hi> continued their <hi>Approaches</hi> but very ſlowly, and we ſaw plainly, that they had no mind to loſe more of their Men.</p>
            <p>At Night they advanced their <hi>Batteries,</hi> and we repaired the <hi>Breaches</hi> their Cannon had made into the <hi>Courtine,</hi> we raiſed alſo a <hi>Traverſe</hi> upon the <hi>Baſtion of Carail,</hi> to cover the Houſes on that ſide from the Cannon of the Enemy. Our Muſqueteers and Gunners fired as they were uſed to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 24th. Early in the Morning the <hi>Enemy</hi> began to play from their new <hi>Battery,</hi> and were for ſome Hours taken up to ruine that part of the <hi>Courtine</hi> that defends the right ſide of the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> and the <hi>Ditch</hi> near it. They threw a power of <hi>Stones,</hi> but few <hi>Bombs,</hi> into our place, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting without doubt thoſe they had ſent for from <hi>Carmag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nole.</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:98932:12"/> They made alſo frequent diſcharges of their Cannon charged with Stones; and during this day and the follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing night they advanced Outworks ſome Foot, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways very ſlowly, by reaſon of the continual Firing of our Men.</p>
            <p>Our Troops having ſuffered great Fatigues, and being much weakned by the loſs of many Men, and ſeveral Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers and Soldiers wounded, ſome of them being kill'd every day, the <hi>Council of War,</hi> having all things well examined and conſidered, the poor condition of the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> reſolved not to defend it any longer, but negligently, ordering him that was to command in this Outwork, to take great care not to be cut off there, and in caſe of an Attack, after two or three diſcharges to withdraw with his Men into the Body of the Place, to put them into the <hi>Courtine,</hi> and to Fire from thence upon the <hi>Half-Moon,</hi> that it might coſt the enemy very dear to be <hi>lodged</hi> there, which was the beſt thing we could do, conſidering the State of our Affairs, the <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guard</hi> being a very hot Poſt, and eaſie to be taken from be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind, was always left to the Guard of 120 <hi>Refugees,</hi> and for a Guard of the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> and of all the <hi>Places of Arms,</hi> which till that day the <hi>Refugees</hi> had been truſted with, there was eſtabliſhed a Body of Men, drawn proportionably out of all our Troops; inſomuch that at Night theſe 200 men were diſperſed in the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> the <hi>Places of Arms,</hi> and the <hi>Gate of Succours,</hi> under the Command of Lievtenant Colonel <hi>de Julien,</hi> who was reliev'd the next day towards Night by the <hi>Lievtenant Colonel</hi> of the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes,</hi> and an equal number of Soldiers. And indeed it was very juſt that ſince the <hi>Enemy</hi> made but one Attack, a <hi>detachment</hi> of all the Bodies ſhould be oppoſed them, without ſuffering that the <hi>Refugees</hi> ſhould be alone ſacrificed, and that the reſt ſhould remain in ſuch places that were not at all inſulted; yet their Commander would not willingly have conſented to this change, in caſe the Council of War had not before re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolv'd to defend but weakly <hi>the Half-moon,</hi> and to abandon
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98932:12"/> it to the Enemy when they ſhould come near it, in order to ſave our Men that were neceſſary to defend the Body of the place, till his Royal Highneſs ſhould be in a condition to raiſe the Siege.</p>
            <p>At Night the <hi>Enemy</hi> advanced their Works within eight Foot of the <hi>Palliſadoes,</hi> they threw a great quantity of <hi>Bombs</hi> into the place, and our men fired briskly upon them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 25th. This Day was ſpent in ſuriouſly firing from both ſides; at Night the Sieur <hi>Fichet,</hi> Lieutenant Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonel of the Regiment of <hi>Salluſſes,</hi> a brave and Gallant man, and an experienc'd Officer, reliev'd the <hi>Commander</hi> of the <hi>Refugees,</hi> who took Poſt that Night upon the <hi>Courtine,</hi> where the reſt of his <hi>Battalion</hi> was. The ſame Night the <hi>Enemy</hi> lodged themſelves upon the Counterſcarp, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding our Firing, and the Work they made was near the Sallying Angle of the Half-moon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 26th. It was reſolv'd early in the morning to make a <hi>Mine,</hi> in order to <hi>diſlodge</hi> the <hi>Enemy,</hi> and the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineer <hi>Guibert</hi> had the direction of it; whereupon they went immediately to work about it, but ſomewhat ſlowly; the day was ſpent in Firing on both ſides.</p>
            <p>At Night the <hi>Commander</hi> of the <hi>Refugees</hi> reliev'd the Lieutenant Colonel of the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes.</hi> It was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved to leave only ſome <hi>Sentrys</hi> upon the <hi>Places of Arms,</hi> to leſſen alſo the Number of the Guard of the <hi>Counter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcarp,</hi> of the <hi>Half-moon</hi> and the <hi>Outworks,</hi> and it was this manner; Into the <hi>Counterguard</hi> were put twenty <hi>Refugees</hi> under the Command of a Lievtenant and a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geant, with order to be always upon their Guard, partly not to be ſurprized, and partly not to be cut off, and to make a great Fire during Night; into the <hi>Half-moon</hi> there were only put 50 men to Fire all night long, and 50 more were poſted into the <hi>Ditch</hi> before the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> having the <hi>Gate of Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cours</hi> behind them, and theſe fifty ſhould every hour re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve the fifty of the <hi>Half-moon;</hi> and in caſe of an Attack,
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98932:13"/> they had orders, after two or three <hi>diſcharges,</hi> to withdraw through the <hi>Gate of Succours</hi> into the <hi>Courtine,</hi> from whence a prodigious Fire was to be made at the firſt Signal that the Half-moon was abandon'd, and after theſe 50 men ſhould be entred by the aſſiſtance of the Fifty that ſhould be in order of Battle in the <hi>Ditch;</hi> the latter ſhould retreat alſo, and ſhould be followed by twenty Soldiers that were placed on the Right and the Left of the ſaid Ditch, near a little <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trenchment.</hi> The <hi>ſurplus</hi> of the 200 men deſign'd for the Guard of theſe <hi>Outworks,</hi> with a hundred that were drawn out of the <hi>Counterguard,</hi> were poſted twenty of them near the <hi>Gate of Succours,</hi> under the Command of a Captain, and the reſt upon the <hi>Courtine</hi> in the <hi>Face</hi> and <hi>Left-Flanck</hi> of the <hi>Baſtion of Carail,</hi> where the <hi>ſurplus</hi> of the Refugees were poſted, except 60 that were put to the Left of the <hi>Baſtion of St. Francis</hi> and <hi>de l'Hoſpital,</hi> who were by turns relieved by the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>During this Night the <hi>Enemy</hi> lodged themſelves upon an <hi>Angle</hi> of the <hi>Counterſcarp,</hi> at the <hi>point</hi> of the <hi>Baſtion of Notre-Dame,</hi> we fired ſuriouſly upon them, eſpecially the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes,</hi> who had their Poſt from this Baſtion till to that of <hi>l'Orme</hi> with all the <hi>Outworks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Enemy</hi> ſpared this Night neither <hi>Bombs</hi> nor <hi>Stones,</hi> and the Latter were very troubleſome to our men. By break of day we ſaw plainly their <hi>Lodgment,</hi> on which they were ſtill at work, and it was ſcarce big enough to cover them by nine a Clock in the Morning. We detach'd ten <hi>Granadeers</hi> of the <hi>Refugees,</hi> under the Command of one of their <hi>Captains,</hi> to ſlip through the <hi>Palliſadoes</hi> of the <hi>Covert-way,</hi> and to throw Fireballs into their <hi>Lodgment,</hi> which was not only punctually executed by the ſaid Captain, but he did much more; for after he had ordered three or four Fireballs to be thrown into the ſaid <hi>Lodgment,</hi> he paſt over the Palliſadoes and leapt into their <hi>Lodgment,</hi> crying kill, kill; whereupon all the Work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ran away with an incredible haſte, and there was not one Soul left behind them, neither in the Work nor the Lines of
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98932:13"/> Communication; and if our Officer had been provided with <hi>Workmen,</hi> he might have entirely ruined their Work; but having no other orders than to make an attempt he retreated. Afterwards the <hi>Counts de Bernez</hi> and <hi>de Rouere,</hi> having diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed with moſt of the Principal Officers about this <hi>Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> which ſhew'd plainly that the <hi>Enemy</hi> had a deſign to inſult the <hi>Bastion Notre-Dame,</hi> it was reſolved that one hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred <hi>Fuſileers</hi> and 60 <hi>Workmen</hi> ſhould make a Sally to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy their Work; 50 <hi>Fuſileers</hi> of the <hi>Refugees,</hi> with ſome Officers proportionably, were appointed for it, being ſuſtain'd by an equal number of the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes.</hi> Both <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tachments</hi> were ready: yet I do not know why their <hi>Sally</hi> was put off for four hours; during which time the Enemy worked with great application; at laſt the <hi>Sally</hi> was made under the Command of a Captain of the <hi>Refugees,</hi> and they had admirable Succeſs; the <hi>Work</hi> was entirely clear'd, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all the <hi>Lines;</hi> and if they had not had Orders not to engage themſelves too far, the Enemy would certainly have had but an ill time on't, conſidering the condition of their Affairs: But if they drive the Enemy out of the <hi>Lodgment</hi> and the <hi>Line of Communication,</hi> they did not execute the reſt, and whether it be for the great Fire the Enemy made, or for ſome other reaſon, the Workmen ſlipt all away, and we were above an hour in poſſeſſion of the <hi>Enemies</hi> Works, without hearing of any of our <hi>Workmen</hi> in order to deſtroy them. The <hi>Enemy</hi> did as we had done in the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned thither as ſoon as our men had order to retreat; and indeed the Honour of this Action coſt us very dear, ſince the <hi>French Protestants</hi> had there two of their Captains, two Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenants, and two Enſigns wounded, and eight Soldiers killed, and fifteen wounded: Thoſe of the Regiment of <hi>Saluſſes</hi> loſt two brave and valiant Captains, <hi>viz.</hi> him that commanded the <hi>detachment,</hi> and another who was Adjutant, and who turn'd that way, either to carry ſome Orders, or only out of curioſity. We were informed, that the Enemy was extream<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſurprized at this Sally, they thought it a very bold Action,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98932:14"/> and during it they ſent ſome Foot to re-poſſeſs themſelves of their Work, but in vain. Some <hi>Squadrons</hi> of the <hi>Enemies Horſe,</hi> that had a mind to be ſeen, were welcomed by our Cannon, and ſent briskly back behind their Courtains. We fired very furiouſly towards the <hi>Enemies Trenches</hi> from all our Poſts that look towards them, and ſome of their Deſerters told us that more than three hundred men of theirs had been kill'd and wounded there. We had this day the welcome News of great Succours that was coming towards us.</p>
            <p>At Night the Lieutenant Colonel of <hi>Saluſſes</hi> reliev'd the Lieutenant Colonel <hi>de Julien;</hi> and whereas a wounded Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant, that was made Priſoner in the <hi>Sally</hi> of the Morning, gave us notice, that the <hi>Enemy</hi> made a <hi>Mine</hi> to blow up the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> and that it was to be executed this very Night, we employed our utmoſt endeavours to bring our <hi>Mine</hi> to a perfection, to be before-hand with the Enemy; but it could not be done that Night. It was reſolved not to leave in the <hi>Half-moon</hi> but ſome <hi>Centries,</hi> and ten Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers upon every <hi>Flanck,</hi> and to let all the reſt March into the place upon the <hi>Courtine</hi> and the <hi>Bastions,</hi> which was executed during Night.</p>
            <p>The Enemy threw a great number of <hi>Bombs</hi> and <hi>Stones</hi> into the place; but before Day-break they took the pains to decamp, without either Drum or Trumpet, leaving us as a ſign of their retreat one of their Canons upon their <hi>Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tery,</hi> which without doubt, for want of Horſes, they could not carry along with them: Neither had they a mind to charge themſelves with a great quantity of <hi>Bullets</hi> and <hi>Fire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>balls,</hi> and a little Powder which they left alſo behind them, in order to ſerve this Place, whenever they ſhall be pleaſed to come again to beſiege it.</p>
            <p>Truly it was a very <hi>ſtrange retreat;</hi> and if we may believe thoſe that have ſeen it, their Troops were in the greateſt diſorder in the World. They left 70 Soldiers and four or five Officers wounded behind them, of which number is the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gineer Vaſel,</hi> and a <hi>Captain</hi> of the Regiment of <hi>Vandome,</hi> and
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98932:14"/> Gentleman to the Prince of that Name. We are aſſured that beſides this number there were more than fifty Soldiers that made a ſhift to creep away, drawing one another, and Swearing and Curſing againſt their Officers and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>June</hi> the 28th. By break of Day we received our Delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance, and we went out immediately to ſee if there was <hi>a Mine</hi> under the <hi>Half-moon;</hi> but we did not find but the beginning of a <hi>Gallery,</hi> and conſidering the manner they were to approach to the <hi>Half-moon,</hi> they were in no condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to be ſoon Maſters of the Place, which indeed ſeems to be preſerved by a particular Favour of God's Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence.</p>
            <p>I will not trouble my ſelf to enquire into the Reaſons that made the Generals of the Enemy <hi>raiſe the Siege,</hi> after a <hi>Blockade</hi> of <hi>ſeven,</hi> and a full Siege of <hi>ten days.</hi> It is enough that <hi>Coni</hi> has been ſaved by the particular aſſiſtance of Heaven, and the Courage and Bravery of thoſe that did defend it. <hi>Prince Eugene of Savoy,</hi> with the <hi>Sieurs de Parelle</hi> and <hi>St. Croix,</hi> arrived between nine and ten a Clock in the Morning, with 2300 Horſe and Dragoons, and near 300 Mules laden with Ammunition; whilſt in the mean time the <hi>Sieur de St. Silveſtre,</hi> with a Body of 2500 Horſe, and 500 Grana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deers, came to join the Sieur <hi>de Bulonde,</hi> in order to go on with the Siege; but he did not arrive till after the <hi>Enemy</hi> had <hi>abandoned their Trenches,</hi> and paſt the <hi>River Sture.</hi> It is reported, that he ſaid to the <hi>Sieur de Bulonde, What, Sir, have you raiſed the Siege, you must return again to it; for the Prince of</hi> Savoy <hi>has no more than 2000 Horſe with him?</hi> To which he replyed, exceedingly troubled, <hi>The Thing is done, the Trenches are abandoned, we have paſt the River, and I will never return thither.</hi> As for the <hi>Sieur de Feuquieres</hi> we have not been able to know yet what Projects he form'd in his Head; but certain it is, that at his return through <hi>Villefalet,</hi> he plaid no more the <hi>Gallant</hi> and the <hi>Gaſcoon,</hi> as he had done when he came to Beſiege <hi>Coni;</hi> a little Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98932:15"/> being preſented to him in this Place, he refuſed to Eat, and gave only ſome few bits to his Dog; and mounting on Horſeback ſaid, <hi>Although the whole</hi> Army <hi>of</hi> France <hi>ſhould periſh, we'll return again to</hi> Coni <hi>and take it:</hi> But he might have been anſwered, That then the Honour of the Action would be <hi>Monſieur Catinat's</hi> due, and that the <hi>Bells</hi> of the Place would belong to the General of the <hi>Artillery.</hi> I ſay this, becauſe at the beginning of the <hi>Siege</hi> the <hi>Sieur de Feu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quieres</hi> ſaid to the <hi>Sieur Ducré,</hi> Lieutenant-Genneral of the <hi>Ordnance,</hi> Morbleu, <hi>Sir, make haſte to put your Cannons upon the</hi> Batteries <hi>to play out of them, before they ſurrender; or elſe you'll loſe the</hi> Bells. And indeed if he could but remember all his <hi>Gaſconnades,</hi> which he has been guilty of during this <hi>Siege,</hi> in his Letters as well as in his Diſcourſe, he would ſo much the more be mortified by the ill ſucceſs of his Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſe. The <hi>French Brigadeers</hi> may very well reproach him with the Troubles he gave them to lie every Night in the Trenches, ſince all their Watchings and Care has been fruitleſs.</p>
            <p>This <hi>Governour</hi> of <hi>Coni,</hi> whom he threatned to hang at the <hi>Gate,</hi> and this <hi>Commander of the Refugees,</hi> whom he would exterminate before his Eyes, with the whole Body that is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his Command, have indeed great reaſon to laugh at his folly; and, for all his Calumnies, to comfort themſelves with the Glory they have acquired, and the Juſtice his Royal Highneſs renders them; having made the <hi>Governour, Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant-General</hi> of the <hi>Marquiſate</hi> and <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Saluſſes;</hi> and preſented the Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>de Julien</hi> with a Ring of great value; and beſides obtained for him from his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> of <hi>Great-Brittain</hi> the charge of Colonel of his Troops. The Marqueſs de <hi>Vauqueres,</hi> who during the Siege has alſo done his duty extream well, and who brought the News of the <hi>raiſing of the Siege</hi> to his Royal Highneſs, received alſo a very conſiderable preſent; the <hi>Count de Bernez,</hi> the firſt <hi>Engineer Guibert,</hi> and Lieutenant-Colonel <hi>Fichet</hi> will not fail to be rewarded alſo by his Royal Highneſs, for the Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:98932:15"/> and Bravery they have ſhow'd during this Siege. In fine all the Troops, Burghers and Militia have exactly done their duty, and it would be too long for me to Name every Body that has ſignalized himſelf on this occaſion: Yet I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not paſs over in ſilence the great faithfulneſs of the People, and the affection of the good Women, who upon all occaſions carried Bread and Wine to the Soldiers, and aſſiſted thoſe that were wounded. The <hi>Clergy,</hi> who did behave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves very devoutly before and during the Siege, did ſing the <hi>Te Deum</hi> with great ſolemnity ſo ſoon as the <hi>Siege</hi> was raiſed.</p>
            <p>Of the <hi>Battalion</hi> of Monſieur <hi>de Julien</hi> there were 12 Officers wounded and 7 killed, 79 Soldiers wounded and 51 killed; in all killed and wounded 149. There are ſtill 25 of them that have not yet recovered of their Wounds, and ſome are in danger of Life. The whole Battalion conſiſted of 500 Men.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98932:16"/>
            <head>ADVERTISEMENTS.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Fleetwood</hi>'s Sermon, Preach'd before the Honourable Houſe of Commons, <hi>Nov.</hi> 5. 1691.</p>
            <p>Diſcourſes upon Trade, principally directed to the caſes of the Intereſt of Coinage, Clipping, and Encreaſe of Money.</p>
            <p>The Monarchs of <hi>England,</hi> from the Heptarchy to their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent Majeſties King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> taken from Medals and Original Paintings, with a compendious Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of their ſeveral Reigns. By <hi>Guy Miege,</hi> Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Regula Placitandi:</hi> A Collection of ſpecial Rules for pleading from the Declaration to the Iſſue.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ars Clericalis:</hi> The Art of Conveyancing explained: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Collection gathered, with great care and induſtry, out of the many Books of the Law; wherein the Nature and Effect of ſuch Deeds, and Inſtruments by which Lands are conveyed from one Man to another are clearly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monſtrated. Alſo the forms and orderly parts which ought to be obſerved in Deeds and Conveyances are laid open and explained.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
